Guide to the John Zuccotti Papers 1956-2015 MS 3018
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Housing & Urban Development (HUD) Files, 1966-1969; 232070; 2.33 Linear feet
  - Revenue Sharing, 1967; 232854 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    Includes mostly print matter concerning federal funding to states, with a HUD summary of a meeting of the Joint Economic Committee hearings on the subject.
  - Open Space, 1968; 232855 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes memos concerning programs and funding for open space land (including vest pocket parks), urban beautification and historic preservation (e.g., Cleveland's interest in using HUD funds to purchase the Astor Theater) in connection with metropolitan development.
  - Mass Transportation, 1968; 232856 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes a draft memorandum of understanding between HUD and the Department of Transportation in connection with President Lyndon B. Johnson's Reorganization Plan No. 2 transfering functions from HUD to DOT (a printed copy of the plan is also in the file); a copy of Senator Jacob Javits's letter to HUD Secretary Weaver expressing concerns about the reorganization; and correspondence related to a dispute over the proposed demolition of a housing project in Cleveland to make way for an expressway.
  - Tenants Rights / Turnkey Projects (2 folders), 1967-1968; 232858 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8-9)
    The label of the original folder holding these documents was "Tenants' Rights." There are some notes and correspondence on that matter. In addition, there are press releases and memoranda on turnkey projects and memos concerning HUD's use of Professional Organization Representatives for advice on policy. The folders also include a copy of The Mayor's Task Force on Reorganization of New York City Government: Report and Proposed Local Law (December 1966) and a related draft note thanking Mayor John V. Lindsay for it, and two papers written by the Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana (CVG) staff: "Planning and Administration of New Towns" (June 1963) and "Recommended Policies for Land Tenure in the City of Santo Tome de Guayana" (September 1963).
  - Bedford-Stuyvesant (Brooklyn, NY) Development Project, 1967; 232862 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-11)
    Includes correspondence, project summaries, and meeting notes, including a package of material for a conference at First National City Bank for the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation and Bedford-Stuyvesant D and S Corporation.
  - Boston Rehabilitation Project, 1968-1969; 232869 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    Includes correspondence and memos about the project, including the script of a proposed movie, concerns about relocation, and a proposed project evaluation by the Joint Center for Urban Studies. Also includes statistics, memos, etc. concerning the Boston Housing Authority and its tenant selection, particularly with regard to "non-white occupancy."
  - Jacksonville (Florida) Housing Authority, 1967-1968; 232870 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13-14)
    Includes correspondence, memos, and a HUD Inspection Division's Report of Investigation concerning an allegation by former Florida governor Haydon Burns that the site for a turnkey project in Jacksonville was not properly selected.
  - Salem (Massachusetts) Urban Renewal, 1967-1968; 232871 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
    Includes memos, correspondence, reports, clippings, and opposition concerning the Heritage Plaza -- East Urban Renewal Area.
  - St. Louis (Missouri) Housing Authority. Pruitt-Igoe Project (2 folders), 1968; 232872 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16-17)
    Includes memos, correspondence, schedules, background reports, and other documents concerning the Pruitt-Igoe housing projects.
  - St. Louis (Missouri). Sports Stadium, 1967; 232873 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
    Includes a memo from Zuccotti to Undersecretary Wood concerning St. Louis's request for HUD funds for a stadium, and Wood's resulting letter to Congresswoman Leonor K. Sullivan.
  - Washington, D.C. Parkchester Apartments, 1967; 232887 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
    Includes memos and press release concerning HUD's project to turn Parkchester Courts into a low income housing cooperative.
  - Memos on Federal Assistance to Various Cities, 1967-1968; 232880 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
    Includes summaries of HUD assistance prepared by Zuccotti for the Office of the Vice President in connection with, at least in some instances, upcoming trips by the Vice President. Cities included are: Atlanta, Georgia; Baltimore, Maryland; Boston, Massachusetts; Springfield, Illinois; Brooklyn, New York; Tallahassee, Sanford, Orlando, and Cocoa, Florida; Indianapolis, Indiana; Louisville, Kentucky; Minneapolis and St. Paul, Minnesota; New York City; Philadelphia and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; Salt Lake City, Utah; and Raleigh, Winston-Salem, and Charlotte, North Carolina.
  - Housing. Miscellaneous, 1967-1968; 232893 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
    Includes various documents generally related to housing, including a HUD circular summarizing its new program under the Housing and Urban Development Act of 1968; a draft description of a grant program for public facilities in low income areas; notes of recommendations from an unidentified task force; the American Bar Association's Special Committee on Housing and Urban Development Law's paper on funding for a program of urban action sponsored by the ABA; memos on potential investments by union pension funds in housing; recommendations of an unidentified task force concerning "Increased HUD Consciousness of Slum Situations"; and a National Research Council paper "The Industrialization of Housing in the United States."
  - Studies on Race Relations, 1968; 232919 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
    Includes a proposal from the University of Chicago for a federal grant to study "The Urban Negro American in the Twentieth Century" and a paper from the Lemberg Center for the Study of Violence "Six-City Study: A Survey of Racial Attitudes in Six Northern Cities: Preliminary Findings."
  - Federal Panel on Early Childhood, 1968; 232928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
    Includes minutes of the panel's first meeting (1 May 1968) and briefing papers and other documents in connection with its second meeting in July.
  - HUD Administration. Miscellaneous, 1967; 232937 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
    Includes a memo on planning a series of center city conferences; a list of general questions about operations; a draft memo from Mitchell Sviridoff about the President's Task Force on Government Organization; and some other minor documents.
  - Edward W. Brooke, 1967; 233036 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
    Includes documents related to Congressman Brooke's expressed concerns about the administration of the low and moderate income program generally and in connection specifically with the Bryant Terrace project in Malden, Massachusetts. Includes correspondence, chronologies, background information, clippings, draft responses from HUD to Brooke, and other documents.
  - Lawrence M. Cox, 1967; 233052 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
    Includes copies of an exchange between U.S. Senator Charles H. Percy and Cox, Executive Director of the Norfolk Redevelopment & Housing Authority, in which Cox expresses support for HUD's administration of a FHA program. Zuccotti's notes and drafts in the file suggest he was consulted in advance of Cox's response to Percy.
  - Jacob Javits, 1966-1967; 233059 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    Includes documents concerning housing-related legislation sponsored by or of interest to U.S. Senator Javits, including notes, Congressional Record tearsheets, and a copy of a letter from HUD Secretary Weaver to U.S. Senator John Sparkman.
  - Edward M. (Ted) Kennedy, 1968; 233076 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
    Includes documents related to HUD's analysis of Kennedy's proposed health care legislation, prepared at Kennedy's request.
  - Robert F. Kennedy (2 folders), 1967-1968; 233092 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29-30)
    Includes copies of memos from Kennedy's office concerning housing, two bills (S. 2088 and S. 2100) sponsored by Kennedy in 1967, a cost analysis of a 1967 Kennedy housing bill, statement by Kennedy introducing S. 3029 (1968), Kennedy's press release announcing his candidacy for U.S. president, and resolutions passed at a 1968 Rural Conference by N.A.C.D. (full name is unidentified but is associated with the National Sharecroppers' Fund).
  - President's Message, 1967-1968; 233098 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 31)
    Includes the advance text of President Lyndon Baines Johnson's speech to the Congress on "Message on America's Unfinished Business: Urban and Rural Poverty" (1967), with related memos from HUD Secretary Weaver and Special Assistant to the President Joseph A. Califano, Jr.; talking points for the president for a meeting with the National Housing Incorporators (October 1968) and for the signing of a bill on interest rates on insured mortgages;, and White House press releases and other documents.
  - HUD Annual Report Transmittals, 1967-1968; 233109 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Speeches by HUD Undersecretary Robert C. Wood (2 folders), 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Speeches. Miscellaneous, circa 1966 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
    Includes a statement by HUD Secretary Robert C. Weaver before the Subcommittee on Executive Reorganization of the Senate Committee on Government Operations on "The Role of the Federal Government in Urban Areas" (16 August 1966); three drafts of a speech (by Robert C. Wood?) titled "Vox Populi, Vox Dei--The Rule of All Good Governments"; a speech labeled "Introduction to Urbana Speech" from the third session of a series of "Centennial Symposia" (1968?); and a two page statement concerning the participatory role of citizens.
  - The Center of Our Society: The American City, 1966 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    HUD publication with the remarks of U.S. President Lyndon B. Johnson at Syracuse on 19 August 1966.
  - Federal Role in Urban Affairs, 1966 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    Includes three books: Part 1, Part 2, and the Appendix to Part 1 of the Hearings before the Subcommittee on Executive Reorganization of the U.S. Committee on Government Operations.
  - Buying From Developers: A Guide to the 'Turnkey' Method of Public Housing Construction (HUD Booklet), 1967 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - New York State Urban Development Acts of 1968 (Complete Text of Law), 1968 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - The House on W. 114th Street, 1968 September (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    HUD booklet concerning a project in Harlem conducted by the New York City Rent and Rehabilitation Administration.
  - Recommendations of the National Commission on Urban Problems, 1968 December 16 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    Includes two copies of Commerce Clearing House's "Special Report" in its Urban Affairs Reports series compiling the recommendations of the Commission.
  - Shoot-Out in Cleveland: Black Militants and the Police, July 23, 1968, 1969 May (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    Staff report to the National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence. Prepared by Louis H. Masotti & Jerome R. Corsi.
  - One Year Later: An Assessment of the Nation's Response to the Crisis Described by the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders, 1969 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    Published by Urban America, Inc. and the Urban Coalition
  - Violence in America: Historical and Comparative Perspectives, 1969 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
    Staff report to the National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence. Prepared by Hugh Davis Graham & Ted Robert Gurr.
- Series IV. Mayor's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Personnel Policy, 1983-1997; 1.17 Linear feet
  In May 1985, New York City Mayor Edward Koch announced that he had formed an advisory committee to examine the management policies and practices of the city's Police Department. The review was prompted by a series of allegations of brutality and other misconduct by the police, often involving African-Americans as the victims. These included the killing of an elderly woman, Eleanor Bumpurs, during a confrontation with police. The committee was to review the recruitment, hiring, medical and psychological testing, supervision, and promotion of officers, and to recommend changes. John Zuccotti, then an arbitrator respected by both management and labor, as well as someone broadly familiar with the city and city departments from his time on the Planning Commission and as Deputy Mayor, was named as Chairman of the advisory group. The nine member panel released its final report about 18 months later, in February 1987. It included about 50 recommendations including random drug testing, higher pay, the expansion of the Civilian Complaint Board to include other than police employees, longer probationary periods, and other measures.
  The series includes the Committee's three volume final report, drafts of some of the sections, minutes of the group's meetings, reference material, and correspondence. The reference material includes information concerning several of the incidents that spurred the creation of the Committee, especially the case of Eleanor Bumpurs. Correspondence includes three letters from Mayor Koch to John Zuccotti responding to the report. Some reports related to police matters dating from the 1990s that were found in Zuccotti's files are also included in the series.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by document type and subject.
  - Committee minutes (2 folders), 1985 June-1987 January (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence, 1983, 1985 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
    Includes resume and application letter of Joseph P. Viteritti, who was hired as Executive Director. Includes a copy of the House of Representatives Subcommittee on Criminal Justice's 1983 "Report on Hearings in New York City on Police Misconduct [Police Brutality]."
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14)
    Includes a report from the Police Department summarizing time committed to training in January 1986; an early draft outline for Chapter 1 of the committee's report (February 1986); information requests; transmittals of clippings; letter of appreciation to Zuccotti from Police Commissioner Benjamin Ward; excerpt from "Report of the Mayor's Commission on Hispanic Concerns," sent to Commission members; and comments on the Committee's preliminary report from James J. Fyfe, Associate Professor at American University in Washington.
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
    Includes Nicholas Mancuso's (President, Uniformed Firefighters Association of Greater New York) comments on the Committee's preliminary report, and Zuccotti's response; draft of Zuccotti's transmittal of the final report to Mayor Edward I. Koch; transmittals for the final bound report; acknowledgements from some recipients of the bound report, including from First Deputy Police Commissioner Richard J. (Dick) Condon; comments from M.C. (Wally) Dobellis, Chairman of the Committee to Save the Police Academy of the Stuyvesant Park Neighborhood Association; and draft proposed statement about the report for Phil Caruso, President of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association.
  - Correspondence. Mayor Edward I. Koch, 1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16)
    Includes three letters from Mayor Koch to Zuccotti expressing acknowledgement, thanks and his particular concern about the Commission's report (February-April) and New York's "Report on the Recommendations of the Mayor's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Personnel Policy" transmitted by Koch (September).
  - Notes & Stationery, circa 1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
  - Press Releases, 1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18)
  - Police Misconduct/Police Brutality, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19)
    Includes copies of two memos sent to Mayor Edward Koch concerning the Eleanor Bumpurs case, in which an African-American woman was shot by police during a confrontation in 1984, and summaries of the Bumpurs and other cases of police misconduct prepared by the Commission (circa mid 1986).
  - Suggested Bibliography, 1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 20)
    Includes the Police Department's suggestions for resources as requested by the Commission.
  - "A Survey of Total Compensation of Police Officers", 1986 September (Offsite-box 6, Folder 21)
    Includes the draft and final of the report prepared for the Commission by Program Planners, Inc.
  - Case Law on Drug Testing for Police Officers, 1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 22)
    Includes summaries of judicial rulings concerning testing prepared for the Commission.
  - Clippings, 1985-1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Police Professionalism in New York City: The Zuccotti Committee in Historical Context", 1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 24)
    Includes the reflections of former Commission Executive Director Joseph P. Viteritti: a typewritten manuscript and two copies of the published version in the "Occasional Papers from The Center for Research in Crime and Justice at New York University School of Law." One of the copies is inscribed to Zuccotti by the author.
  - Preliminary Report, 1986 November (Offsite-box 6, Folder 25)
    Includes a draft (November 7) and the final (November 10).
  - Draft: Findings & Recommendations, 1986 July (Offsite-box 6, Folder 26)
  - Draft: Executive Summary, 1986 September (Offsite-box 6, Folder 27)
  - Briefing Paper, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 28)
  - Draft 5: Chapter 2. Selection, 1986 November (Offsite-box 6, Folder 29)
  - Draft 4: Chapter 3. Training, 1986 October (Offsite-box 6, Folder 30)
  - Drafts 4 & 5: Chapter 4. Promotion, 1986 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 31)
  - Draft 5: Chapter 5. Internal Investigations & Discipline; Draft 6: Chapter 5. Command Discipline & Supervision, 1986? (Offsite-box 6, Folder 32)
  - Draft: Final Report, Vol 1, Findings & Recommendations, 1986 December 24 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 33)
  - Draft: Final Report, Vol 1, Findings & Recommendations (2 folders), [1987] January 5 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-2)
    Report is dated January 5, 1986, but this is obviously a mistake and should be 1987. The accompanying transmittal shows the correct year.
  - Draft 3: Chapter 1. Introduction to Volume 2, 1987 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mayor's Advisory Committee on Police Management and Policy. Final Report. Volumes I, II, and III. (3 folders), 1987 February 24 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4-6)
    Bound copies of the final report. Vol I: Findings and Recommendations; Vol II: Overview of the Department; Vol III: Supporting Documents.
  - Print Matter, 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
    Includes the Police Department "Official Roster" of November 1985 and Annual Report for 1985.
  - Police Arbitration Panel, 1991 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
  - Commission to Combat Police Corruption (2 folders), 1997 October (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
    Includes three printed reports from the Commission: Performance Study: The Internal Affairs Bureau Command Center, Monitoring Study: A Review of Investigations Conducted by the Internal Affairs Bureau, and Second Annual Report of the Commission.
- Series V. Speeches and Other Presentations, 1967-2015; 3.25 Linear feet
  The series includes materials related to Zuccotti's appearances as a speaker on various occasions over the years. Perhaps the most coherent part of the series are the opening files, which include speeches, remarks and logistical briefing notes for Zuccotti's years in the 1970s on the City Planning Commission and as Deputy Mayor, and for a few occasions after the 1970s. Much of the series, however, includes working files for the 1980s and forward, that is, files of rough outlines and reference materials, often associated with multiple or unclear events. To the extent that some of this material was found together during processing, it was kept together, such as the file of material used in the 1980s to recall the New York City fiscal crisis of the 1970s. Most material though was found disorganized and was fashioned into rough chronologies or themes by the processing archivist. Detailed content of these working files is noted in the container list. The series also includes syllabuses, readings, some student work, and other material related to Zuccotti's work as an adjunct law professor at Yale in the mid-1980s and at Columbia in the 1990s.
  The series is roughly organized, opening with files of identifiable speeches and writings, followed by working files of reference material and notes. The series closes with files related to courses Zuccotti taught at Yale and Columbia.
  - Speeches. City Planning Commission and Deputy Mayor. Binder Content (2 folders), 1973-1977 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Speeches and Briefing Sheets (8 folders), 1975 September-1977 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13-20)
    Includes remarks, drafts, itineraries, talking points, programs, logistical information, and other documents related to remarks delivered by Zuccotti while Deputy Mayor. Organizations include, among others, Local 237 Teamsters Health and Welfare Fund, Lincoln Square Neighborhood Center, Annual Music Awards Banquet, 100 Black Men, Sydenham Hospital, Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association, the new Health Systems Agency, Convention of Sanitation Officers Local 444, testimonial dinner (with program) for Dr. Jose E. Arraras, Christian Brothers Boys Association, New York Law School Alumni Association, Proxmire Committee, Real Estate Board of New York, HEW Secretary Joseph Califano, Civil Service Technical Guild, New York Market Radio Broadcasters Association, Work in America Institute Conference, American Jewish Congress, and Celanese Corp. Includes an Executive Summary of the report from the Mayor's Management Advisory Board (1976)
  - "Turning The Profit Motive to Public Advantage", 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 21)
    Includes the agenda and other advance materials for this seminar sponsored by the New York City Law Department's Economic Development Division and Columbia University Center for Law and Economic Studies. Includes the transcript of Zuccotti's comments as panelist on the subject "Integrating the Public Process with Private Sector Development Techniques."
  - Speeches (Folder 1 of 5), 1992, 2002 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 22)
    Includes remarks at the Downtown Lower Manhattan Association (1992) and remarks and other documents for the Cornell Real Estate Conference 2002).
  - Speeches (Folder 2 of 5), 2004, 2006 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes "Against All Odds--Why New York Works," Zuccotti's keynote address before the Toronto Real Estate Forum (2003); multiple copies are found in the following reference/working files suggesting that its themes were commonly drawn on. Also includes a "speech not given" to an unidentified audience (2006).
  - Speeches (Folder 3 of 5), 2009, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes remarks presenting an award to Richard Kahn (2009); at the dedication and unveiling of the America's Response Memorial at the Winter Garden of the World Financial Center (2011); and at a conference "Battery Park City: Coming of Age" (2012) presented by the Steven L. Newman Real Estate Institute.
  - Speeches (Folder 4 of 5), 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    Includes brief remarks to Family Office Exchange; at the Manhattan West launch; and the Veterans' Day wreath-laying (2014).
  - Speeches (Folder 5 of 5), 2015 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes remarks for memorial service for Lloyd Kaplan and Zuccotti's introduction of Bronx County Supreme Court Justice John A. Barone at the Rapallo Award ceremony of the Columbian Lawyers Association. Documents for the Barone event include the program, menu, and a letter from Barone apparently in response to a condolence letter from Zuccotti in connection with Barone's mother in which Barone reflects on her life.